<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on ⚡Arunav Konwar⚡</title>
        <link>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on ⚡Arunav Konwar⚡</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 07:55:12 +0530</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>COVID-19: Why listening to data shouldn’t be a political issue</title>
            <link>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/2020/07/covid-19-why-listening-to-data-shouldnt-be-a-political-issue/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 07:55:12 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/2020/07/covid-19-why-listening-to-data-shouldnt-be-a-political-issue/</guid>
            <description>A cautionary tale on politicising data Arunav Konwar
As I look at the COVID-19 dashboard by the Johns Hopkins University while I write this on 9th July 2020, I see over 3 Million cases of COVID-19 in the USA, more than 1.72 Million cases in Brazil, and over 700K+ cases in India being reported, rounding up the top 3 countries. Needless to say, the virus has gone out of hand and 2020 marks the end of almost a decade long global economic growth post the 2008 financial crisis.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="a-cautionary-tale-on-politicising-data">A cautionary tale on politicising data</h3>
<p>Arunav Konwar</p>
<p>As I look at the COVID-19 dashboard by the Johns Hopkins University while I write this on 9th July 2020, I see over 3 Million cases of COVID-19 in the USA, more than 1.72 Million cases in Brazil, and over 700K+ cases in India being reported, rounding up the top 3 countries. Needless to say, the virus has gone out of hand and 2020 marks the end of almost a decade long global economic growth post the 2008 financial crisis. Northern Italy, with some of the best healthcare systems in the world, was overwhelmed by the sheer number of patients at the height of the pandemic. Similar stories in New York City, Boston, and many major cities around the world. It’s July now and with the curve failing to disappear or even flatten I couldn’t help but wonder, how did we end up here? Could we have done things differently?</p>
<p>What binds all of these above stories together is a common thread of policy and enforcement failures at multiple levels within governments around the globe. An amalgamation of unpreparedness, indecisiveness, bad governance, and turning a blind eye to data, and politics itself. It’s a cautionary tale of how vulnerable modern economies are and how things can spiral out of hand, and that too very fast.</p>
<p>The first possible hints of coronavirus were reported to the World Health Organization (WHO) as pneumonia of unknown cause in Wuhan, China on December 31, 2019. The time it took for most countries around the world to notice and act on it astonishes almost anyone now looking back at the unfolding events. The U.S is a prime example of failing to heed to early warnings. The country and its leaders refused (and still refuses) to lockdown and officials failed to enforce the guidelines laid down by the WHO, even after repeated warnings from experts. Unfortunately, this is still the case in the U.S, Brazil, and many more countries. Politicians with their own agenda have been seen misrepresenting data and calling for re-opening the economy. Similarly, the U.K government failed to lockdown the country on time and let massive events such as the widely popular English Premier League keep on continuing. These massive events leading up to the eventual lockdown have been traced back to as avenues for the spread of the virus in the country.</p>
<p>Although some experts say that the Indian government had the foresight of locking down early, a mistake it and many other countries made is reopening the economy at a time when the infection curve was still on the rise. The pressure to reopen the economy had been high since the day India went into a full lockdown on March 25, and this pressure likely interfered with the government’s re-opening decisions. Global consultant McKinsey’s report from April said India&rsquo;s economy must be &ldquo;managed alongside persistent infection risks&rdquo;. The reopenings could have been done in a more data-driven manner which optimized for both the recovery of the economy and the well-being of the people.</p>
<p>This finally brings us to the case of Taiwan, an island country in the South China sea with a population of around 23 Million, which has become a case study on how to tackle a pandemic like this. Their success is in no part an accident. They have been at the forefront of adopting the latest technologies that can inform their leaders and policymakers, and help pave a path towards drafting effective policies to tackle such major outbreaks. Taiwan leveraged its national health insurance database and integrated it with its immigration and customs database to begin the creation of big data for analytics. This combined with online user reporting systems and timely SMSs to people with different categories of risk (categorized by data analytics) created an effective system to both inform and keep their citizens safe.</p>
<p>Establishing such a framework to tap into existing data is not only sensible but also an insurance policy against similar future situations going out of control. This calls for the establishment of permanent data-driven departments within government agencies to deal with similar future outbreaks. In recent times, travel, fueled by globalization, urbanization, and climate change has accelerated the potential for new outbreaks. According to the WHO, there are 7,000 signals of potential outbreaks every month. This in itself should be a compelling reason for the adoption of big data analysis in policy and governance to make sense of the massive amount of data in our everyday lives. A combination of machines distilling the data and humans interpreting it and enforcing actionable items provides us with the best line of defense against such future events.</p>
<p>Taiwan established the National Health Command Center (NHCC) in 2004 following their experience with the deadly SARS outbreak. Due to this existing infrastructure and the foresight to look at data to understand the situation, the Taiwanese officials were able to start responding as early as January 5, 2020, by boarding flights coming from Wuhan and taking temperature readings of people.</p>
<p>While the application of such data-driven decision-making frameworks can be different for each country, the need to implement them while taking care of security and privacy concerns is of utmost importance. Finally, we need to remember that behind every statistic is a human life associated with it. In the end, it’s as much a social problem as it is a data problem.</p>
<p>And for leaders worldwide, this global fallout of COVID-19 can be a reminder for them that problems like these transcend politics and can only be solved through listening to data and experts.</p>
<p>The results are clear, the governments that made decisions based on data were more likely to bring pandemics under control. No matter how harsh lockdowns and other social distancing and sanitization measures seem, doubling down on our fight against COVID-19 seems to be our best bet to beat it. And this needs to be enforced by the government even when under the intense pressure and opposition of certain sections of the society and especially the political opposition.</p>
<p>Finding the optimal balance between reopening the economy vs keeping the infection rate low needs to be informed by data and not through emotions, and certainly not through politics.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>COVID-19 Map - Johns Hopkins Coronavirus Resource Center (<a href="https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html">https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html</a>)</p>
<p>McKinsey_coronavirus' impact on India (<a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/india/getting-ahead-of-coronavirus-saving-lives-and-livelihoods-in-india">https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/india/getting-ahead-of-coronavirus-saving-lives-and-livelihoods-in-india</a>)</p>
<p>COVID-19 and global epidemics are becoming more frequent. This is why (<a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/03/coronavirus-global-epidemics-health-pandemic-covid-19/">https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/03/coronavirus-global-epidemics-health-pandemic-covid-19/</a>)</p>
<p>The global economy is woefully unprepared for biological threats. This is what we need to do (<a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2019/03/our-economy-is-woefully-underprepared-for-biological-threats/">https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2019/03/our-economy-is-woefully-underprepared-for-biological-threats/</a>)</p>
<p>NHCC - Taiwan Centers for Disease Control (<a href="https://www.cdc.gov.tw/En/Category/MPage/gL7-bARtHyNdrDq882pJ9Q">https://www.cdc.gov.tw/En/Category/MPage/gL7-bARtHyNdrDq882pJ9Q</a>)</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Thoughts on bias in facial recognition technologies</title>
            <link>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/2020/05/thoughts-on-bias-in-facial-recognition-technologies/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 07:55:12 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/2020/05/thoughts-on-bias-in-facial-recognition-technologies/</guid>
            <description>Problem Statement With the onset of new Artificial Intelligence (AI) technologies one of the most pressing problems within countries is their indiscriminate use on their own people. This deployment represents a seismic change in the way countries police and surveil their own citizens. On top of being a surveillance tool it brings with itself more immediate issues such as bias in facial recognition. According to Joy Buolamwini, a researcher at MIT who specializes in understanding AI technologies, these facial recognition technologies are more likely to mis-identify people of color, which especially is a reason for concern for a country like India.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="problem-statement">Problem Statement</h2>
<p>With the onset of new Artificial Intelligence (AI) technologies one of the most pressing problems within countries is their indiscriminate use on their own people. This deployment represents a seismic change in the way countries police and surveil their own citizens. On top of being a surveillance tool it brings with itself more immediate issues such as bias in facial recognition. According to Joy Buolamwini, a researcher at MIT who specializes in understanding AI technologies, these facial recognition technologies are more likely to mis-identify people of color, which especially is a reason for concern for a country like India. Colorism in India was historically linked to caste systems in medieval ages across the Indian subcontinent, and furthermore fueled by the presence of the British. Thus, use of AI technologies represent a monumental challenge with the potential for creating or reinforcing existing biases.</p>
<p>The potential benefits of facial recognition are way too many for governments and organizations to pass up. With understaffed offices and lack of people with the required level of expertise, facial recognition and other AI technologies can be a major factor in the quest towards revamping the workforce and the economy. But this lack of representation of people of color susceptible to colorism in the datasets pose a challenge in building AI systems which are equitable. The challenge is especially so because being mis-identified by automated systems may mean the difference between receiving or missing out on government benefits, employment opportunities or something worse, like being incorrectly charged for crimes by law enforcement agencies.</p>
<h2 id="proposed-solution">Proposed Solution</h2>
<p>I propose a multi-step approach to solving this issue. First, Policymakers need to enforce policies which encourage government bodies to adopt Privacy and Security principles (which include, but not limited to: Avoid creating and reinforcing existing bias, Be Socially beneficial) at each step of any process involving adoption or procurement of AI technologies, failing of which the work may not proceed further.</p>
<p>Second, the Government needs to leverage the data on the Aadhar platform while keeping privacy and security issues in mind. According to the latest figures as of 31 May 2020, the total number of Aadhar enrollment is at 1.25 Billion. This represents over 90% of the current Indian population. It’s an immense database of facial information covering a diverse set of facial features across the Indian mainland. Any exercise to source such a diverse dataset by individuals and organizations would prove to be prohibitively expensive thus putting the government in a position to leverage this as a platform for training data sourcing.</p>
<p>Individuals and organizations can be granted access to training data using a new AI technique called Federated Learning. Wikipedia describes Federated learning as a machine learning technique that trains an algorithm across multiple decentralized edge devices or servers holding local data samples, without exchanging their data samples. Research suggests that application of this technique can be achieved at scale required for India while preserving privacy.</p>
<h2 id="major-obstaclesimplementation-challenges">Major Obstacles/Implementation Challenges</h2>
<p>There always exists a possibility that this unprecedented access to facial data can be misused. Thus, legislation to facilitate access using robust multi-tiered authorization levels is required. Policy makers need to determine where the lines of appropriate use should be drawn and furthermore, help enforce policies with certain checks and balances that prevent a misuse of these actions.</p>
<p>India, being endowed with a quasi-federal form of government, has local governments who may not support policies drafted at the central level due to different local needs and challenges. Thus local governments with discussions with activists of their respective locations can help legislate policies which can be used as a testing ground for a broader implementation of policies at the central level.</p>
<p>Admittedly, this is not a policy that central authorities would ideally like, but it is one with the highest potential supporters, largely thanks to discourse at the lowest level. By working towards a society that is inclusive of all of its citizens, our community is strengthened and all people are afforded their constitutional right to equal opportunity.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Buolamwini, Joy (2018). “Study finds gender and skin-type bias in commercial
Artificial intelligence systems”
<a href="http://news.mit.edu/2018/study-finds-gender-skin-type-bias-artificial-intelligence-syste">http://news.mit.edu/2018/study-finds-gender-skin-type-bias-artificial-intelligence-syste</a>
ms-0212</p>
<p>Shankar, Ravi (2007). &ldquo;Fair Skin in South Asia: an obsession?&rdquo;. Journal of Pakistan
Association of Dermatologists. 17: 100–104
<a href="http://jpad.com.pk/index.php/jpad/article/viewFile/695/668">http://jpad.com.pk/index.php/jpad/article/viewFile/695/668</a></p>
<p>Mishra, Neha. (2015) &ldquo;India and
Colorism: The Finer Nuances&rdquo;. Washington University Global Studies Law Review.
<a href="https://openscholarship.wustl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1553&amp;context=law_globa">https://openscholarship.wustl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1553&amp;context=law_globa</a>
lstudies</p>
<p>UIDAI. Retrieved 31 May 2020
<a href="https://uidai.gov.in/aadhaar_dashboard/index.php">https://uidai.gov.in/aadhaar_dashboard/index.php</a></p>
<p>K Bonawitz (2019). Towards Federated Learning at Scale: System Design - arXiv
<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1902.01046">https://arxiv.org/pdf/1902.01046</a></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Cloud Native Journey</title>
            <link>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/2019/11/cloud-native-journey/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 07:55:12 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunavkonwar.github.io/posts/2019/11/cloud-native-journey/</guid>
            <description>This is an article describing my journey into the cloud-native ecosystem and how I got around to exploring it.
I first got around to learning about cloud-native technologies was around winter days of January 2019 when I was based in Munich, Germany. I was part of a program with the Technical University of Munich (TUM) where I was working on building skills to identify and solve problems in our daily lives using technology.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an article describing my journey into the cloud-native ecosystem and how I got around to exploring it.</p>
<p>I first got around to learning about cloud-native technologies was around winter days of January 2019 when I was based in Munich, Germany. I was part of a program with the Technical University of Munich (TUM) where I was working on building skills to identify and solve problems in our daily lives using technology. We learnt about solving issues using agile and design thinking menthodologies.</p>
<p>As part of my role I was expected to develop solutions involving Machine Learning pipelines that had to be hosted and scaled online. I learnt there that this thing called Kubernetes can help me achieve just that. This was the first time I heard of this new technology. Previously I had heard of dockers and used it in experimental learning setting without any real life use-case, but this docker, I learnt, was used in conjunction with Kubernetes to achieve things previously unimaginable.</p>
<p>We learnt about Kubernetes by directly delving into hands-on exercises which led through installing and running Kubernetes on the Google Cloud Platform (GCP). I learnt how the system stayed up even when one or two of the containers went down for some reason. I realized its importance to the commercial and the mission critical processes. Apparently gone were the days when big sites needed to be taken down for maintainence. There would be no need of downtime in the upcoming future. I liked this idea.</p>
<p>Following this I was always curious about applying this to my own projects but I was practically limited to using it for myself in a local setting. This was enough for me to get a good idea of the inner workings of the technology and resulted in my giving a small talk about it as part of the Developers’ Circle meetup in Munich, Germany. It was a good time introducing so many new people to the technology and reminded me of the time just a few months before when I was introduced to it for the first time myself.</p>
<p>I finally got around to attending my first ever cloud-native themed conference, the amazing KubeCon + CloudNativeCon 2019 North America at San Diego, California. I had always read about it and seen photos of the conference on Twitter and finally it was my time to be part of it. It was a surreal experience to finally meet the people behind the technology in person. San Diego and Southern California as a whole is a gem of a region. Sunny and always fun to be around. I liked the looks of the blue skies and the warm beaches, and add to it the amazing conference, it was an unbeatable combination.</p>
<p>I had an incredible time chatting with core maintainers and contributors at the Contributors’ part and the New Contributors’ summit. The contributors party was set in the old quarters of the San Deigo city and provided a very cozy and warm setting for everyone to talk, have a few beers, eat tacos and enjoy each others’ company with the fun Karaoke set up.</p>
<p>The day following the party provided an opportunity for all new/intermediate contributors to come into the same page through an amazing session. People were given the overview of the organization and how everyone contributed to the codebase and the checks and balances that was present to take care of the quality of the code and the ecosystem. I was amazed at the sheer scale and the thought process that might have created this whole structure. We managed to pull off a very productive time exploring the Kubernetes codebase. Everyone turned out to be very warm and friendly and seemed always happy to help out. I felt at home.</p>
<p>The main conference seemed like a theme park with thousands of people roaming around. Never have I ever seen 12,000 people sitting and attending a talk together under one roof. The sheer scale of the ecosystem came into light then and right there. I liked the setting where people post-keynote broke off to attend hundreds of smaller talks around the conference venue. This gave me an opportunity to attend and meet some core maintainers and engineers of some products I loved, for example Spotify. I loved their talk on how they leverage the power of cloudnative technologies to serve millions of people around the world their favorite songs right at their fingertip without fail.</p>
<p>Everything else after the keynote was even more surprising. The variety of products being developed around the ecosystem was up for show as I saw all the different startups in their booths. This perfectly represented what seemed to be a very sustainable ecosystem between the open-source and commercial world. I remember everyone being very enthusiastic about showing their products and taking time to understand people’s problems and coming back with suitable solutions for them.</p>
<p>One of the highlights of the conference was meeting Joe Beda and talking with him about technology and how my research work related to the conference. It was a short and a memorable chat, after which he signed his book for me. I carry the book around with me as a quick reference for the technology and also as a reminder of the amazing time I had in San Diego.</p>
<p>I look forward to being active in the community and contribute to the overall organization. I hope to attend many more of the amazing conferences the community puts up around the world and keep the fire inside alive.</p>
<p>Arunav Konwar</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
